<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue and complaint made vpon the siedge of Oastend, made by the King of Spaine, the Archduke, the Infanta, the Pope, the Prince Morrice, and the eldest sonne of Sauoye. Translated out of French. Also a true discourse of that which is hapned in the same towne of Oastend, from the fourth day of the moneth of February 1602. VVith certaine newes written towards London, from Italy, Fraunce, Hungary, and other places</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848831</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848831</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1552:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue and complaint made vpon the siedge of Oastend, made by the King of Spaine, the Archduke, the Infanta, the Pope, the Prince Morrice, and the eldest sonne of Sauoye. Translated out of French. Also a true discourse of that which is hapned in the same towne of Oastend, from the fourth day of the moneth of February 1602. VVith certaine newes written towards London, from Italy, Fraunce, Hungary, and other places</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Read] for Mathew Law,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A fanciful dialogue.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ostend (Belgium) --  History --  Siege, 1601-1604 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13947:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13947:1"/>
            <p>A Dialogue and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made vpon the ſiedge of Oaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, made by the King of Spaine, the Archduke, the Infanta, the Pope, the Prince Morrice, and the eldeſt ſonne of Sauoye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo a true diſcourſe of that which is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> in the ſame towne of Oaſtend, from the fourth day of the moneth of February 1602.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ith certaine newes written towards</hi> London, from Italy, Fraunce, Hungary, and other places.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for Mathew Law. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:13947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13947:2"/>
            <head>A Dialogue and complaint vpon the ſiedge of Oaſtend, made by the King of Spaine, the Archduke, the Infanta, the Pope, the Prince Morrice, and the eldeſt ſonne of Sauoye.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Mightie God, what miſfortune, O what cruell miſhap it is to ſee this ſmall place which hath ſtayed the valour of ſo many good ſouldiours, and cauſe an armie to be conſumed before this pettie place. Alas it was well tolde me what diſcommoditie I ſhould indure before this citie: A citie I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erme it, for <hi>Caeſar</hi> before <hi>Munda:</hi> howbeit much good was loſt, yet not ſuch ſtore of people, as I haue loſt before this: for I may with trueth ſay, that I haue within theſe foure moneths loſt fiue thouſand men, or little leſſe, and among them many va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Collonels and Captaines, and yet I ſée not apparence to get the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Infanta.</speaker>
               <p>My brother is ſtrong enough to beare all, both men and money required to this warre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Siſter, whatſoeuer I could do for the preſeruation of this Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh countrie, I ſweare I haue effected to my power.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, your maieſtie hath ſufficiently ſatiſfied the promiſe of the late Catholick king.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The king of Spayne.</speaker>
               <p>To my Father I haue promiſed for euer to maintayne the Apoſtolique ſiege, and that which he gaue to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>Sir your greatneſſe is ſufficiently knowne in perſuing of this with ſo great charges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13947:3"/>
               <speaker>The king of Spayne.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt kéepe this countrie in awe, leaſt if in <hi>France</hi> came troubles, I might hereof poſſeſſe my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>That ſhall neuer be ſéene? No Frenchmen hath deſire to ſée (as they haue ſéene) the Spaniards in their townes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The king of Spayne.</speaker>
               <p>Some foole will be found among ſo many vnfit, who for gould will aduance my power.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>The Frenchmen haue a king, who is not to be prouided, and I do more feare that they will enter in this countrie whilſt I am buſie here, and cauſe the countrie wholy to rebell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The king of Spayne.</speaker>
               <p>This king was at <hi>Calles,</hi> whereat I greatly meruaile: for I cannot conceiue what he had to doe there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>He was at <hi>Calles</hi> not without hauing ſome affayres, but it hath troubled my braynes to thinke what it ſhould be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The king of Spayne.</speaker>
               <p>Do you thinke that this king would haue falſefied his fayth, and he would endeauour to get his countrie by craft.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>The falcifying of his promiſe imported not ſo, he thereby may get good profit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>There neuer was french king who would ſo wrong himſelfe as to breake the promiſe of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>It hath little béene ſéene, that any heretofore ſuch, haue ſuch recompenſe as this king ſhould haue by falcifying his oath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>I do greatly wonder to what purpoſe the Duke of <hi>Biron</hi> went to England.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13947:3"/>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>I durſt lay, that it is about war and nothing els that he made that voyage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>And the Duke of <hi>Anguillon</hi> who came towardes you, of what did he ſpeake to you of peace or of warre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>He was ſent to yéeld, ſuch as he hath done by the great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of my horſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Then to this peace let vs not repoſe, but it is requiſite that euery one be ready to reſiſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>It is well the right meane to preuent that no ill hap come to vs, but men cannot reſiſt euery where.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>What is then to be done? you muſt anſwere to this point? doe you hope ſhortly to be maiſter of this place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>It doth conſiſt in God to effect ſuch wonder and not in any humaine power.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you then hope? that in looking on the ſame it will through wearyſomneſſe it will yéeld it ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>If it had not béene for your maieſty, I durſt not haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to come neare the ſame by halfe a leage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>It hath béene <hi>Spingnola</hi> who cauſed me to be commanded quickly to take the ſame, to the end there to place gallies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>Your maieſtie ought not to haue promiſed to take this place, or at the leaſt not ſo ſoone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13947:4"/>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>We haue to moch ſpoke thereof tell me I pray you ſonne, whether you meane to take it, or els to depart from thence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>If it had not béene for ſhame, I would before this time haue gone away from thence, for I through obſtinacie haue wholy ruyned my campe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Séeing you cannot get it, leaue off your will which you haue ſo bent againſt the ſame place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Flaunders</hi> hath furniſht all which my army would haue, therefore I cannot from hence depart without diſhonor? but they would be weary I know their humour. And then when they would, they are at ſuch great charges that they haue not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> power to ſupport the ſame. And though I ſhould yet remayne here foure monethes, expecting good ſucces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I neuer ſhall haue hope to take the ſame, I did well thinke at the firſt what would become hereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you beléeue that this <hi>Morrice</hi> would make peace if hée were thereto requeſted by ſome mighty prince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>I haue heretofore promiſed him the prouince of <hi>Holland,</hi> ſo he would yéelde to be my ſubiect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſéeing he had refuſed the ſame, what ſhall we then doe to get him with vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>To pray the Pope to be a meanes therein, for perchaunce he may perſwade him thereto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>That cannot be ſo, for it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them to frequent him by reaſon of their beliefe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:13947:4"/>
               <speaker>The Archduke.</speaker>
               <p>This peace may be concluded like that of <hi>France</hi> for he dooth onely fight for liberty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine to the Pope.</speaker>
               <p>Holy father I am now come to your holines with prayers vnto you, to take ſo much paines as to perſwade (if it be in your power) the eſtates to yéelde themſelues, and to promiſe vnto <hi>Morrice</hi> and them that yéelding themſelues to me, they ſhall be moſt happy for I will promiſe them liberty of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Pope to the King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>My ſonne you haue wrong, For all my ſkill doe I imploy to draw thoſe people from their erronious way, wherein they doe perſiſt, and will you haue me ſuffer them to continue therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Holy father pardon him, who with griefe doe not know what to ſay, I ſpeake it for a trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Pope.</speaker>
               <p>I would ſatiſfie you, if it did conſiſt in my power and that I had authority ouer them but the eſtéeme not of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>Holy father you haue the one halfe of the ſhame and I haue the other halfe, and all the dammage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Pope.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne, it is very difficult to finde an end, I know that you haue receiued great loſſe and dammage, and loſſe againſt thoſe people many regiments of Spaniſh ſouldiers, and eke many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of other nations, but all thoſe which there do dye, haue full forgiuenes of their ſinnes, which cannot chuſe but to be a great comfort to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The King of Spaine.</speaker>
               <p>I doe feare that in time they will preſſe mee ſo ſore
<pb facs="tcp:13947:5"/>
placed in Ambaſſage, tell me I pray you from whence come thoſe words.</p>
               <p>Truly from <hi>Madrill</hi> towardes this troubleſome repoſe, who ſéeing he cannot get vs by the way of armes, dooth go about to entice vs with his flattering charmes, but let him not truſt to it, he ſhall effect nothing therein. Men ſhall ſooner ſée the deceaſe of vs all, then a Spaniard commaund in this countrie of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Therefore trouble not your ſelfe any more about this peace, but rather pray to God for the deceaſe of the king of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,</hi> that you may repaire thether and ſuccéede him, and of his crowne poſſeſſe your ſelfe. And touching the Archduke, feare not, for I do hope that he will not long liue, and then that it ſhall be my fortune to be married with your Aunte, ſo you may pray to God for her and mee together, and I hope wee ſhall well agrée.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13947:5"/>
            <head>A true diſcourſe of that which is <hi>hapned in the Towne of</hi> Oſtend <hi>ſince</hi> the fourth of Februarie. 1602.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ithence the generall aſſault done vppon <hi>Oſtend</hi> laſt by the Archdukes forces, there hath not beene any great matter attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for in the Campe was ſome mutinie for paye, but with money and with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere puniſhment ſuppreſſed againe, and more forces were ſent for ſome helpe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, of fiue hundreth thouſand duccats out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> are apay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Antwarp,</hi> and they ſay, that there was hope of ſome mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſhould be deſtinated thetherward, for to furniſh moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two hundreth and fifty thouſand duccates, ſo that by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall obſtinacie of the houſe <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the ſiedge is reſolued to continue, yet the Artchduke is ſayd to be ſubiect to the falling ſickneſſe, and that he hath fallen vpon his ſword and ſomewhat hurt his left ſide.</p>
            <p>The vnited prouinces are likewiſe reſolued to defend the towne, and do ſend more men, and change the olde gariſon for new, and ſome two companies out of the towne had their maſt ſhotten off, and ſo did driue vpon the ſtrand a ground, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and are all carryed to <hi>Bridges,</hi> but it is thought they ſhall paſſe by ranſome as they do accuſtome, they within haue made of late ſome notable ſallies with great victory, and diſtroyed likewiſe ſome platforme a making without, by the which their
<pb facs="tcp:13947:6"/>
ſhippes vpon the coaſt of Britayne, ſome ſeauen Spaniſh ſhips vittelars which meant to go to <hi>Kenſall,</hi> and more other nations, it is ſayd ſome eight or nine hundreth men to be drowned there on ſhoare.</p>
            <p>In In <hi>Scotland</hi> the Quéene is deliuered of another ſonne.</p>
            <p>In the vnited Netherlandes is made an aſſociation for to trade in the Eaſt Indies, wherein be comprehended all the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>Amſterdame</hi> for a halfe, they of <hi>Zealand</hi> for a quarter part, they of <hi>Enckuyſen</hi> and they of <hi>Rotterdame</hi> for another quarter part. In which company euery man is admitted that bringeth in his mony, ſo that the ſame trade wil be of a great conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Oſtend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since the day aforeſaid is reported that ſome 32. companies are of late entred into the towne, alſo how that the Archduke is gone to <hi>Bruſſell,</hi> being ſickly, and how that the Infant his wife ſhould be minded to leaue the Netherlands, and become Quéene of <hi>Sicilly</hi> or <hi>Portugall.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13947:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
